Guide to the Records of the Central Congregational Society and Church ARC.086
Brooklyn Historical Society
Records of the Central Congregational Society and Church
1854-1945
Brooklyn Historical Society
Central Congregational Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
ARC.086
11.6 Linear Feet in 10 manuscript boxes, five flat boxes, and one oversize photograph folder.
This collection documents the activities of the church from its creation in 1854 to its consolidation with the Clinton Avenue Congregational Church in 1942. The collection is largely composed of ledgers with financial and membership information.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Cadman Memorial Congregational Church, 1989.
Existence and Location of Copies
Item-level description and a digital version of the photograph from this collection is available for searching via the image database in the library under the object ID prefix V1990.57.
Historical note
The Central Congregational Society and Church was founded in 1854 and originally located at the corner of Fulton Street and Classon Avenue in Brooklyn, N.Y. Throughout the late 19th century, the church remained in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn, and was led by the Rev. J. Clement French, the Rev. Dr. H. M. Scudder, and the Rev. Dr. A. J. F. Behrends, respectively. In 1900, upon the death of Dr. Behrends, the church selected the Rev. Dr. Samuel Parkes Cadman (1864-1939) as pastor. Dr. Cadman became the leading Congregational clergyman in the United States, as well as the first U.S. radio preacher.
In 1939, the Central Congregational Church was renamed in memory of Dr. Cadman. The church merged with the Clinton Avenue Congregational Church in 1942 at the latter's location, and afterward came to be known as the Cadman Memorial Congregational Church, presently located on Clinton Avenue at Lafayette Avenue in the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn.
Sources:
"Central Congregational Church." Brooklyn Eagle, April 24, 1854, 2.
"Dr. Cadman may succeed Dr. Behrends." New York Times, December 18, 1900, 2.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The collection's digital surrogates should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Scope and Contents
This collection, covering 1854 to 1945, contains correspondence, ledgers, minutes, deeds, bills, sermons, publications, one photograph, and one composition book of the Central Congregational Church and its affiliates. These records provide a window into the church activities and membership during the late 19th and early 20th century. Ledgers and minutes created throughout regular activities of the church document members with addresses and years of membership, baptisms, and church accounts, and may be of use to genealogists. One sepia-toned photograph shows the interior of the Central Congregational Church at 64 Jefferson Avenue, Brooklyn, N.Y.
Church records and registers -- New York (State) -- New York; Church history; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Religious life and customs; Genealogy; Membership lists; Photographs; Minutes; Ledgers (account books); Bulletins; Financial records; Receipts (financial records); Church property -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Property -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Cadman, S. Parkes (Samuel Parkes)
- Series 1: Administrative and general materials
  - Papers relating to church properties, 1844-1919 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photograph of church interior, circa 19th century; V1990.057 (Box XOS Prints by Accession 2)
  - Sermons of Dr. J. F. Behrends, 1888-1900 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
    Scope and Contents
    Three copy books.
  - Sub-series 1.1: Correspondence
    - American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, 1918-1931 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - American Committee for Armenian and Syrian Relief, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - American Missionary Association, 1919-1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Auld, William Muir, Rev., 1912 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Humstone, W.C., 1919-1921 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Pierce, George I. and other treasurers, 1918-1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - General, 1918-1937 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Sub-series 1.2: Minutes
    - Trustee minutes, 1856-1873 (Box 2)
    - Board minutes ledger, 1871-1909 (Box 2)
      On page 129, there is a transcription of Dr. H.M. Scudder's resignation letter, dated October 23, 1882.
    - Loose materials from board minutes ledger, 1871-1905 (Box 2, Folder 2-8)
    - Minutes: Deacon's meeting, 1928-1930 (Box 3)
  - Sub-series 1.3: Member lists and pew rentals
    - Member Lists (with addresses) and baptisms, 1882-1895 (Box 11)
    - Member Lists (with addresses) and baptisms, 1891-1906 (Box 11)
    - Pew rental records, 1896-1908 (Box 3)
    - Pew rentals, 1906-1912 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Pew rental records, circa 1916-1919 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Pew rental records, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Series 2: Financial records
  - Cash book, 1902-1904 (Box 12)
  - Passbooks, 1903-1912 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Cash book, 1904-1909 (Box 4)
  - Ledger, 1905-1907 (Box 13)
  - Parish House improvement bills, 1908-1910 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Ledger, 1911-1913 (Box 14)
  - Ledger, 1914-1915 (Box 15)
  - Income and expenses, 1919-1932 (Box 5)
    There are loose receipts tucked into a pocket inside the front cover.
  - Cash book, 1920-1925 (Box 5)
  - Cash book, 1925-1927 (Box 6)
  - Income and expenses, 1927-1930 (Box 6)
- Series 3: Publications
  - Annual reports, 1894-1940 (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
    Missing 1895-1898, 1911-1917, 1922, 1933, 1934, 1936, 1938.
  - Programs for special services, 1921-1940 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Church calendars, 1921-1940 (Box 7, Folder 5, Box 8, Folder 1-6, Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Central Congregationalist, 1927 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Central Messenger, 1927-1940 (Box 9, Folder 3-6, Box 10, Folder 1)
    Missing all of 1928 and 1930 and also scattered issues elsewhere.
  - World War (WWI) activities, 1917-1921 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Series 4: Sub-organizations
  - Ball and Chain Club: Treasurer's report, 1935-1941 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Business Women's Club Minutes, 1927-1932 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Committee of Church and Society minutes (St. Paul's Church and Central Congregational Society?), undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Simpson Auxiliary of Women's Foreign Missionary Society: Receipts and disbursements, 1908-1924 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Simpson Auxiliary of Women's Foreign Missionary Society: Minutes, 1934-1940 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Women's League of Clinton Avenue Community Church: Account book of receipts and disbursements, 1924-1940 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Women's League of Clinton Avenue Community Church: Minutes and financial reports, 1937-1940 (Box 10, Folder 9)